Introduction.
Radiation therapy to the head
and neck area involves
some amount of radiation
that goes into the mucosal membranes.
The mucosa are the membranes
that line your mouth and throat
to produce saliva and fluids,
to allow you to eat and drink well.
Unfortunately, radiation to these mucosal
areas leads to inflammation, sores,
and pain in the mouth and throat,
which we call mucositis.
Fortunately, we have a set of rinses
we would like you to do from the start
of radiation to help lessen the amount
and degree of mucositis.
First and foremost,
we need you to take care
of any dental procedures
prior to starting radiation.
The reason is that
radiation will cause your teeth, gums,
and jaw bones to take longer to heal
after any surgeries,
root canals, fillings,
crowns, or procedures.
We ask that if you have not had a dental
cleaning and dental X-rays
within the last six months,
to please make an appointment
to see your dentist as soon as possible.
If you do not have a dentist, we can
have you seen by our UCLA dentistry team.
As for your dental hygiene,
please use a soft toothbrush and continue
regular brushing during radiation.
If toothpaste is irritating, it's
okay to use just water when brushing.
Be gentle in areas
that may become sensitive.
If flossing is challenging,
you can stop flossing.